um on the rest of those questions and
we're also going to be
producing a document that addresses them
so please keep your
questions coming in um and i also just
want to say that
the three of us jason juliana and myself
are members of the black members
standing committee
okay so um i've been told
to kick it off uh so here goes and then
i'll pass you
over to the others um
so so what i want to do is just give you
um a few points on what i think
that decolonizing institutions could
mean
um and also a few points on how we've
been going
about it in peel so what does it mean
um when we talk about decolonizing
institutions in education
i may be wrong but i think that most
people
are right by now comfortable with the
idea that a lot of what we've learned
in schools and colleges and universities
has been based on what we call colonial
knowledge
or knowledge that took for granted the
superiority of the west
which was itself derived from imperial
dominance
equally i think that just a little
reflection on each of the disciplines
that we learn
and teach and research would illustrate
their roots to be intrinsically
connected
to imperial progress from anthropology
to
zoology and also show how
they're influenced by power dynamics in
our contemporary world
that dictate the importance of certain
types of research
and scholarship over others
we also know that the unfamiliarity
the strangeness of our predominantly
white
higher higher education institutions has
very real
effects on the life chances and
educational attainment
of people who are not white
educational institutions especially
universities are predominantly
white spaces faces that don't reflect
the multicultural nature
of british society black people
who do go on to higher education are
least likely to get promoted
or rise to the top of their profession
we know that the reasons for this don't
lie
in some spurious notion of merit
or deficit it's because our black
students
don't see themselves their stories
their histories their culture as given
any importance in the curriculum that
they study
the examples influential thinkers prize
winners and toppers
of their disciplines are all from the
global north
and usually male this profound
imbalance is what the agenda to
decolonize
institutions tries to address and it's
up to us
as workers in the field of education
to try and think out how to go about it
as a number of people have been saying
lately and as the gist of so many of the
questions
that you posed when we announced this
webinar suggests
it's not the why of decolonization
that's
at issue it's the how so how
do we decolonize our curriculum let's
not be
afraid of this process as educators this
is something that we do
quite well we rethink we review
we constantly change what we teach what
we learn
what we research decolonizing isn't
about
taking away or destroying knowledge as
the headlines of the daily mail or the
daily telegraph which suggests
it's about broadening out our
educational resources
from case studies to paradigms to draw
from
insights research and knowledge from the
global south
as well to check that our learning
materials and learning spaces
are inclusive to simply be more aware
of the inequalities of our disciplinary
canon
educators have done this before the
1960s and 70s overturned a lot of the
syllabi
of the past we can do it again it is
after all what higher education is about
not to regurgitate a static body of
knowledge or churn out
expertise in a time-honored canon but
rather to critique
convention to question social norms to
create new knowledge
to change society and offer different
perspectives
on scholarship at keele we began
thinking about decolonizing about two
years ago
we had a great cohort of students who
were really motivated
by what was going on in cape town and
cambridge
and london and during the ucu strike
that year our equality officer
in keele ucu bulent gokay built a
teaching program
with the students and a number of us
colleagues
to start pushing to decolonize what we
were teaching
learning from decolonizing groups across
the globe
we created a decolonizing keel manifesto
and organized a number of events
inviting everyone
in the university this created a space
for colleagues
and students and even some members of
the senior management team
to talk about what decolonizing keel
could possibly mean
whether its practice across the globe
was relevant to keel
and what we could learn from it at one
of these events
lola olive family the then women's
officer at cambridge university student
union
told us about how she and her fellow
peers had tried to decolonize the
english
curriculum at cambridge another event
a colleague of mine talked about gender
and decolonization
another spoke about how to decolonize
the phenomenon of so-called
world music i i gave a talk
about the worrying take-up of
decolonization in india
where it's it was and is being used by a
very right-wing
and populist government to further an
islamophobic and high caste agenda
so we were really trying to tease out
what it was and how we as teachers and
researchers
were looking at it this coincided with
keel working on a race equality charter
award from which
everyone could see how race affects
staff progression
and student attainment in really stark
terms
this all converged to make decolonizing
a central
university concern we're now in the
process
of revere reviewing all of our modules
in all subjects
and conversations are beginning on how
to help colleagues
in sciences as well as humanities look
again
at how we can all make our curriculum
more inclusive and decolonized
however this also raises issues about
the hidden
curriculum or on the way that
institutions are structured
who makes the strategic decisions in
each of these institutions
where does the power really lie it's no
surprise i think that a lot of the drive
behind decolonizing keel kane at the
same time
as a pensions dispute and industrial
action
along with it just as it's no surprise
that during our covid context
especially affecting black lives as well
as the horrific murder in minneapolis
that sparked off
the black lives matter movement
decolonizing the curriculum is back on
the agenda
this has also raised other concerns
especially
now that the agenda has been endorsed by
the university as a whole
how can we prevent it from simply being
a symbolic
tokenist tick box management led
exercise that will not achieve anything
or affect
any change the most important aspect
that we continually emphasize
at keele is the centrality of student
engagement they are the ones who pressed
it as a demand at the beginning
we need them to keep us on our toes now
we know that the most long lasting
enduring innovations
are generated from the shop floor when
students and teachers work together
that's the most important thing
with all the challenges facing the
higher education sector
in the coming academic year especially
in regard to delivering the
new normal i hate that of blended
learning
and teaching decolonizing the curriculum
may seem less of a priority it could
easily
slip off um slip down the agenda or even
off
we must keep it there i think
extraordinary times call for
extraordinary projects in adversity
higher education has often altered the
status quo
the settled way of doing things um
it's it's been the agent of change
not conservativism there's no reason why
it can't be that again okay
i'm gonna stop i've actually come in
within the ten minutes so that's that's
pretty amazing for me because
usually i'm told i talk too much um
we're now going to go
on to juliana
okay okay so um i'll try not to
go over what celine has said and um just
to
give an overview of uh what we
understand
uh decolonization of institutions to
mean
and um and whether we think the new is
not a
thing and to look at why we need to
decolonize
and what our responsibilities are
towards this
um so the declination of institutions
agenda is a process whereby powerful
institutions such as the universities
and colleges and so on
um attempt to and i say attempt to
because that's what a lot of them are
trying to do
read themselves colonial and imperial
vestiges that have been used to exploit
oppress and suppress others who were
seen as powerless
um be it because of their nation their
race or their class or their gender or
even their sexuality
so um this process is by no means a new
thing
um however with corvid and with the
death of george
floyd and the black lives movement it
has gained a new momentum and so
we need to seize this opportunity and
and hopefully bring about some concrete
changes in
within the institutions and and the
system uh to ensure that those uh most
in need and those who suffered uh
structural inequality are reflected
within these
with these institutions at all levels so
um so who responsibility is that
um the responsibility is all of us it's
for all of us to decolonize our
institution
it's not just because people tend to um
say oh the black worker should always
you know do this and do the other but
it's not solely the responsibility
of black workers is the responsibility
of buddhist workers in their
institutions and so on
however it does require commitment
and a willingness on all of us
to play our part in changing the
narrative that's been established over
the
over centuries um you know by those with
the power to set up these institutions
so
the um as i said before it's not a new
thing
african scholars have been writing about
decolonizing the institutions
decolonizing
institutions such as religion um
churches politics economics the media
more than anything you know people like
ivan van serkuma
henry clark walter rodney chancellor
williams uh people like amateur of ghana
osman samban of senegal
angela davis and fiongo of kenya france
fanon
all of these people are in recent times
we've had time uh
but to name a few who have been working
and tirelessly pushing
for this agenda to to change
the other people that we often tend to
uh tend to forget
in this whole process of the call for
decolonization
is black parents because in the 60s when
black parents came
black people came into this country and
earlier as well
um a lot of young black children went
into the schools
and their knees were not being reflected
were not met and
a lot of people were failing in the
education system some of them were put
into
educationally some normal uh classes so
on
and so um there was a lot of
underachievement and so black children
were not coming out with a qualification
that they require
in order to attain and go on to
university or get a better job
so a lot of black parents there was a
movement of black parents who are
pushing for
a better education because they
recognize that the education system has
mis-educated their children
um and so and so some of the parents as
well since some of them were teachers in
the countries that they came from said
set up
voluntary uh groups to teach their
children the basic skills
so this is where we have um things like
the saturday schools and
um set up and summer school measures and
so on
um to ensure that the children are
getting the skills that they require
and lastly we have students in terms of
people who have been pushing for this
change
black students and other students as
well
uh both in britain and those who are
coming from overseas
asking for the curriculum to be
decolonized we
we've had um shalini mentioned the thing
about rose must fall
um you know campaign by the student the
the
students and ucla students been asking
you know why is our curriculum white why
are we not having
a representation of black lecturers in
our
uh institutions and so on why are we um
having book lists that's predominantly
white writers
and so there was a lot there's a lot of
uh push for for this change so why do we
need to decolonize our institutions so
we need to reflect the interest of all
people and appreciate all cultures
within our student institutions and
uh and curriculum uh that we work and we
the lecturers working and we're teaching
and our students are learning in
we need to recognize other cultures
contribution to the world civilization
and heritage
you know so other cultures matter as
well in terms of our teaching
and cultures have a past world so we
need to
know a lot about the ancient egyptians
the west african
uh east africa north african uh
civilizations
azotech the incas the ghana empire the
mali empire the mohenjo-daro
and harappa civilization all of these
people
had all of these empires had
well-developed system
before the onset europeans and these
need to be
in the education system so it's
important that we know
what went on before the europeans came
into
the shores of this country we need to
decolonize because the institution need
to read themselves and the curriculum of
all the historical misconceptions that
we've had
about black people about people of color
and so on and and one of the first rule
of denying a people of their right to
live
really is to deny them their narrative
you know
history their language or scientific
development and a lot of that has gone
on in africa
it's also about breaking down their
stereotypes to get rid of the education
institutions
uh ignorance and racism which is
institutionalized and has been
ongoing on a on a day-to-day basis
it's important that you cater educators
themselves for our verse
in uh in the field are the ones who are
actually delivering them
you know so it's no point having um you
know
somebody who's black who can teach black
history
and then you say to them oh guarantee
something else um you know when they've
actually
made it clear that they can teach that
particular area go and teach european
history for example
you know which is something that they're
not versed in um
and and the thing to remember is that
black history or any of these subjects
it's not just for black students it's
for all students
you know if we're informed we will
hopefully act differently
what it does as well for the black
students to to have a much more
um diverse curriculum is that it gives
them a a sense of self-esteem
and and and and improves on their mental
health well-being as well
so again it's the thing about confidence
um that we want to see imbued in our
black students as well
now when googie was younger one of the
persons i mentioned
and in my beginning session
um talks about you know the importance
of education he talks about the role of
education
and culture in our education systems and
he talks about and he has a question
what is the relationship between
education and culture and transforming
the economy political and the social you
know so
and for him education is part of culture
and vice versa
and so you cannot have a situation
um where you have an education system
that transmits a particular
idea and they expect other people
everybody to
to fall in line or to gain from it so um
for him education should give people
knowledge of the world in which they
live in
how the they have shaped the world and
how the world have also shaped them
you know so for him he's talking about
an education that gives us a worldview
that
that frees up our minds and so on and
that might sound like
something too radical but it isn't
actually um
so he talks about we know what kind of
education are we talking about and then
he says that things like
um you know depending on who's holding
the power
you know education can either be used to
eliminate
um our reality or it can be used to mask
the reality that we're faced with
and um and and he says in in
you know in in a situation where you
have a structured society where one
nation or race or class or gender
uh dominates another as is the case in
britain
there can never be a neutral education
transmitting neutral culture
so this is a key thing is that the
education system that we have at present
time
that has not undergone decolonization
does not transmit a neutral culture it
transmits a culture that
suppresses and preserve the existing
order
and keeps those classes those nations
those races those
gender under control in the way that
they present their stuff
and he gives this illustration of a and
b you know
um a being the person who's oppressing
the exploiter
the suppressor and then you have the b
who's the one who's being exploited and
so on
and the question is that what kind of uh
education would you want that person to
have
you know so so depending on your
position you would be the one to decide
you know who would have um uh the kind
of education that they will get
so um so what that exemplifies really is
colonialism
you know the ruling class or nation
imposes rule and control
over groups of other people that they
subjugate us uh
and the aim is to really to control
their rep their productive forces
uh and then colonize their minds as well
um
and what this is what this shows is that
you cannot have this
without political control and without
cultural control
and that can be direct or indirect
in the way that is carried out
so we do need to decolonize our
curriculum because it benefits everybody
it benefits everyone it benefits uh the
students the benefits the
the the institutions it benefits is it
is in our interest to decolonize uh what
we're teaching
you know so and it's important that we
teach um
history that teaches us uh about the
lives of other cultures
that what they have contributed to the
world and on and
their um their participation in the
world activities and so on and what they
have
um what their pensions and
uh their art their uh could create their
language needs to be other needs to also
be recognized
in the curriculums so i'll i'll stop it
up out there and then i'll
pick up the questions later and add a
bit more to it
thank you
jason hi um first and foremost
um good afternoon everyone um i hope
everybody's keeping well
um i feel really privileged to be
sharing this platform with um celine and
juliana
um thank you to everyone for taking the
time this afternoon to be here
um and also for chris um for organizing
it and the fantastic work that rebecca's
doing
in terms of interpreting um in the first
instance
you know shalini and giuliana made some
fantastic comments and what i don't want
to do is go over
those fantastic points i think what's
really important is to kind of really
engage with this idea of
what you know colonizing means and you
know i always say i'm yet to meet two
people that have the same conception
um of that idea and kind of shalini
mentioned that earlier
and juliana spoke about the idea of it
being a collective endeavor you know
it's a collective
engagement it's a collaborative
engagement that requires all of us
to engage in this line of work because
there's a benefit
all of us living in a multicultural
diverse society
i think the diluting of histories
is an interesting thing and there is a
historical amnesia that is usually talk
about
issues around decolonizing you know and
black history and other indigenous
histories
within that i think importantly what i
want us to kind of move towards is kind
of thinking about
you know solutions how we come up with
solutions for this
i think one of the most important things
is really framing
this discourse around how we
create you know more practical solutions
around how we address this
i think for many years the child has
been left at academics of color um and
student activists
and actor and community activists and
while all of that
endeavor is much needed and it's and
it's been relied upon
in many respects it's also been
exploited um it's
you know often that labour is
unre-enumerated it's
um it's not rewarded physically in the
same ways and i think what's really
important to think about how we can kind
of receptually
reconceptualize decolonization but more
importantly besides the actual
work on the front line obviously
really thinking about what the work
behind the scenes looks like and i think
a lot of that comes from how we change
our cultures in terms of our
institutional cultures in terms of where
it resides
and think about actually questioning the
function of the academy
what it is what is its fundamental
purpose you know it's to
inherit all these canons of knowledge
but actually who are the gatekeepers to
this knowledge
more importantly how do we challenge
those space but i kind of want to prefer
two or three suggestions i think might
lend itself some of these ideas
i think fundamentally we need to kind of
think about what inclusion looks like
and when you kind of think of
decolonizing
a strand within that or strand within
inclusion is decolonizing
i think that inclusive aspect becomes
really important now if we think about
the dominant eurocentric cannon
it does the complete opposite that it
excludes people it marginalizes people
it keeps individuals on the periphery
of understanding their own histories and
understanding how that makes up
um their facialization and their
understanding of the world
so i think one of the most important
things is really think about how we
engage in this side of an inclusive
framework what does that framework look
like um and within different
institutions you'll inherit different
ideas and different things
but fundamentally it's about thinking
about how do we adopt the word inclusion
do we use it for the kind of benign
purposes
if we're talking about the decolonizing
flooding becomes really important
because what we need within that
is actually we need to center black
students
and black stars and we need to kind of
really kind of encapsulate those ethnic
minority voices
really to kind of center this argument
to think about how we
engage with this in a more inclusive
kind of dialogue
i think importantly this endeavor needs
to be resourced properly
um from a human resource point of view
and a fiscal resource print
so we need to we need to kind of move
away from the exploitation of
fame labor in relation to this issue and
move towards more
um strategic aims over prolonged periods
of time that will look to address this
which need to be appropriately funded
and really um and really engaged with
the idea that actually as julian has
said
that everyone's benefit to engage in
this dialogue and money needs to be put
behind this
so for example continuing professional
development where staff may not feel so
comfortable engaging with this
um ensuring that the labor itself is
renumerated
so if individuals particularly fame
individuals going to be tasked with
beer heading this agenda within
institutions that they are enumerated
for their time and their labor
and this goes towards aspects of career
progression
because often famed staff are not
in a situation where this this kind of
labor is valued and it goes it actually
isn't acknowledged by senior
stakeholders within universities
and that is problematic because that is
exploitative in itself
i think the contours of racism mean that
the idea of decolonizing and declining
energy is changing all the time
we're finding you know keeping abreast
of racism
as a new omnipresent thought
that reinvigorates itself and
camouflages itself in so many different
ways
means that we have to be agile and
vigilant to what decolonizing means
in these current violent and divisive
times
and to that end i think it's really
important that we kind of think about
what allyship looks like in mobilizing
the colonized decolonization
so for example the reconceptualization
of
gene polarization it really requires
people to think about okay
in the spaces that we reside in what
does that allyship look like
how can we dismantle these kind of
initial structures beyond
reading list assessment diversification
what else can we actually do
it's about challenging those spaces
those
those gatekeeping spaces where knowledge
is confined to
this dominant white eurocentric canon
it's about challenging those spaces
in all of its insidious over and over
formed as a structural and systemic kind
of
tim symbol of you know
coloniality as we see it i think that
becomes a really really important thing
but in thinking about how we do that is
important particularly for white allies
to think about
how we you know impact that space
and ensure that that engagement is
collegiate
rather than as i've often spoken about
is that you know a seasonal approach
it needs to be four seasons as opposed
to one and not
a really important thing um going
forward
i think it's really important just to
finish on a couple of points
i think the idea of collective endeavor
is
important more now ever we live in
divisive times
and to be quite honest bain people are
exhausted there's an exhaustion
there's a lethargy that's set in with
doing this work i haven't done it for so
long
now it's time for all of us to carry
this burden and i also talk about
you know within that it's important to
acknowledge that women of color
particularly black women have really
been burdened with this work and an
acknowledgement that as a
man of color black man i need to do more
i need to think about how i engage in
these spaces
and how i do that before i kind of think
about you know pointing the finger
anyone else the first person i look at
is myself
and i'm always thinking about ways in
which i can engage in that labor
and ensure that it's equal endeavor as
opposed to
it being unweighted endeavour and
heavily in the fact that women of color
been doing this late
i think most importantly it's collective
we all have to engage in it and i think
it's important to kind of think about
the promise of university who
universities embody
what is their function towards society
and in many respects they are microcosm
of society
and in being a microcosm of society we
have to engage in history
that reflect that society over a
prolonged period and i mean a global
society
not just one that's situated within the
global
north specifically but i think that's
really really important
i just want to finish by saying that i
think in these really difficult times
and in
in the wake of black lives matter and
everything that's happened i think it's
important and i'm guided by
a saying that i heard recently actually
in a documentary i watched about hillary
robin clinton
i know she's a divisive figure but she
said something i actually thought was
really really powerful
for these times and she derived it from
an old methodist saying
and it says um we all need to do all the
good we can
do all the people through the ways we
can
i couldn't think of a more way framing
this kind of collective endeavors
all in it together that's brilliant
thank you so much for your time it's not
lost on me that it's the middle of the
day and people are taking the time to
engage with the friend
but thank you so much and really looking
forward to engaging with all of you
it's been
thank you thank you uh jason thank you
juliana
um so what we're going to do now is as i
said before we
we picked out um three questions each
from the 100 or so questions that we uh
um that that we were faced with um
uh over the weekend so um i'm gonna
uh and what we're going to do is we're
going to read out our questions
and then respond to them so i will kick
off
again my first question is
which disciplines seem to be
more colonized from amongst natural
and social sciences
uh and uh my response is that i mean i
guess we can explore all of our subjects
using
this this decolonizing lens and that
some subjects have been
better at doing it than others so for
example
subjects like english and history but
there are a classroom of disciplines
that emerged
in the age of enlightenment which is a
period that was
intrinsically connected with imperialism
and slavery um so sciences uh
that are based on a hierarchical system
of classification
of different phenomena sciences like
biology chemistry
geology but also social sciences like
economics and law and others that came
later
subjects like anthropology and sociology
as well um
and and just looking at it from this
decolonizing lens it sort of explains
why for example
students in newly independent african
nations
where you were actually using european
specimens
in their geology lessons in the 1960s
okay so um so that was my very brief
response to the first question
the um the second question i'm going to
look at is
how do students how to get students
involved
and participate in this process
hopefully i address some of this in in
my actual talk
but i would say uh i would say we need
to work with
the student union we need to work with
students
in different societies as well um we
need to organize
workshops collectively um you know
in in workshops where they are equally
involved and we also
need to um we need to go with their
initiatives that's certainly something
that we
thought was really important at keele
and in the classroom we need to nourish
their curiosity
if they bring up stuff that we don't
know it's actually okay to
learn from our students i was reading
the other day
about a music student who was
who tried to talk about rap at her
university a very prestigious
university um and she was faced with
ignorance uh and you know yeah we don't
know
everything but i think we need to be
willing to learn
from our students and rethink from them
my last question i'm going to look at is
a
complex question what are the major
issues in the use of the concept
decolonized in the hee sector unless
we're clear about what it mean
what we mean by it can we use it
successfully
to disrupt and dismantle established
hierarchies
i i do actually agree with the premise
of this question
um and i think that um jason
addressed it as well you know
decolonizing
can perhaps mean so much that it
actually
i mean potentially it could end up
meaning nothing at all
um and yeah you could say
that perhaps decolonizing is simply an
academic exercise about the stuff that
we teach and research
and stick to that but i i do think that
it's also connected with what i talked
about you know the hidden curriculum
that i that i mentioned
um and and also um you know it might be
that we make most
difference um most decolonizing
difference in the classroom
um effectively but but i think it would
it's also good that we
engage as anti-racist activists
in our unions and our workplaces too
okay juliana your questions yeah
okay so my question um
is about um
about um declinizing the curriculum in
fe
um if we can give particular example um
well the example i can give is is
sheffield
um but it was in the past and
one of the things we have to maybe do is
to revisit some of the things that have
been done in the past
that has worked and looked to include
those in what we
were wanting to do now and and one of
the things i'd like to do first of all
is to
um give tribute to some of the young
people who participated
in the black lives matter's movement in
sheffield
because some of these young people were
people who were
teaching in saturday schools after
school clubs
and summer measures and some of them
went through the access program
as well as well as doing a levels as
well and one of the things we did do in
sheffield
is that um we that there is a
uh they had set up a black access
program because it was recognized
that black people were not going through
their system in terms of
getting education getting qualification
going into workplace
and um you know having a place there and
working on earning
income and supporting their families and
so on and and contributing to society
and so what the black community did was
to fight for
the black access program after the riots
took place and all the rest of it
now that program produced curriculum
that was different from what we teach
you know every other
day in the schools because the students
needed to understand
how we come to be where we were you know
what is said
in the system that's created the
condition that they find themselves in
and especially some of the black men who
found themselves always
um you know at odds with a with a legal
system or with
the police and all the rest of it and
they needed to understand what is it
about our history
that's created a situation whereby we
are hated so much
and you know there's a lot of racism
against them and um that has resulted in
that being institutionalized to the
extent that they can't get qualification
so what we did was to um devise a
curriculum
that had at its core black history
and this is not a history that tells you
oh how wonderful africa was or anything
like that or
the caribbean or the americas or the uh
india
and pakistanis but to really look at the
concrete
contributions black people have made
over the years
to the the the world history and then
they're not the way not on the periphery
at the beginning they were
at the core of all the activities that's
going on so
the whole idea is to start by looking at
what was there before the europeans came
you know
what changed why did it change you know
the whole thing about historical change
and so on but at the same time we were
giving students the tools of analysis
to underlie society so they were looking
at things like you know in terms of race
nation
class gender analysis and so on
and looking at how that impacted on on
their being but also they were
developing skills
of evaluation interpretation and all the
rest of it all the academic skills that
they will need for higher education
so that gave students a lot of
confidence so first of all they knew who
they come to it's the thing about their
identity they come to know who they are
and and why they they are in the
situation that they're in
and what they need to do in order to
move forward and so these are the kind
of thing with it and how to
challenge racism within institutions and
how to deal with microaggression when
when it
when it comes to them and so on so those
are kind of thing um
you know that we did the other thing
with the the community did in sheffield
was to
run after school clubs and so on where
some of these issues were replicated and
black children um gained from that
so that but the cuts actually has
impacted on this provision and so
because of the cuts
a lot of this provision um had gone to
the war
okay so this the what was the second
question again the second question was
about
um
exam boards i think yeah but it's
something about the examples
um i had a discussion with my daughter
about this when i was thinking about
this and
and she was saying things like well the
examples you know um
need to be a bit more diversified you
know they members need to be diversified
the curriculum itself needs to be looked
at again it's back to the whole thing
about the curriculum because the
curriculum drives what
was taught uh in the books for example i
know i noticed that recently
uh and even in the books or i used to
teach sociologists on some of the
examples some of the
imageries that are portrayed there are
so negative
so for example you have a picture of a
black student a white student the black
white student is projected
at the forefront and black students are
at the back you know of that whole thing
so
that sends a subliminal message that you
know they're not important
they must also use research as an
example
done by black black lecturers or black
researchers or black writers or
intellectuals
not just the white sounding um you know
uh
white names and so on they must also
depict black people in a positive way
you know so and they must have within
their decision makers
a lot of some diversity in terms of
black
markers black exam board setting
questions and all the rest of it so we
need to have that
um and i just wanted to mention that one
of the things that students found out
was that
in terms of games development um
courses there's often this notion that
oh you know it is
white uh people who developed it but the
reality is that
um there's a lot of black game uh
developers
and and when students do their research
they find that there are and and
lecturers also need to learn from that
um
are you looking at the last question
julia um what can be done okay yeah and
look at the last question the last
question is about
visual awareness this is great um
we need to see more examples of black
people
in positions in in positions of power
impositions in in pictures and uh
around the colleges and institutions and
so on uh we need to see more drawings of
them illustrations of people like
officials are people like mary seco uh
people like
um william coffey claudia jones
um you know all the people who are
involved in uh movements and so on
martin luther king malcolm x
angela davis all of these people need to
be given
prominence but also we need to see
pictures of the students who have
achieved
in the colleges in the universities i
went to one
college in birmingham and they had these
pictures of
students who have achieved and how much
you know they had achieved and where
they went to university and the kind of
subject that they studied
you know so that's quite important but
also aside from that we also need to
know
uh in concrete terms the number of our
students who are going into
universities that's going to do medicine
to do law to do
dentistry and so on and not just um
you know um have them as pictures we
need to have more black staff
and and um and not just token
appointments
uh in positions and so on
and i just wanted to add add to that
that um
one of the things that jason mentioned
is the thing about we
really to be more reflective and i think
for us to
be able to teach or do a lot of this
stuff we really need to
uh be able to need to be looking at the
way um we look at
things ourselves as as educators
we need to decolonize our own minds and
so on
okay so um and we need to be we need to
prepare be prepared to learn about other
cultures as well
so thank you thank you
jason all right thanks again
um just to follow on from the points
made from
made by cellini and juliana i think one
of the most important things is really
thinking about
this idea of resistance and very often
in terms of
the white fragility aspect there's often
kind of this wall of resistance that one
encounters
which can be really difficult in terms
of managing this discourse and it's
almost
you know a violence that people of color
experience you know
they face the kind of the visceral
experience of racism
and then it's that kind of violence
having to manage the emotions of white
people within this dialogue and
you know robin d'andrea talks a lot
about this in terms of racial
in terms of white fragility and i think
one of the things in terms of
the question in terms of how we tackle
resistance amongst colleagues um
i think that this is a really important
thing i think
one of the things that um i wouldn't
like to say that i've conceded this
but i accept is that people
some people are not returning some
people's heads are not returning and
i sometimes think it's better that we
kind of engage with those who
actually want to make change i actually
think there's a
more there's a bigger mass of people
that want to create change
and cultivate a new conceptualization of
what belonging
inclusion decolonizing could mean and i
think that
that is where our energies should lie um
i think in relation to the question how
do we tackle resistance most probably
who think
this is unnecessary i think if they have
that mindset in the first place
and attempts have been made to try and
change their way of thinking
i think that that is wasted energy i
wouldn't focus
my energy on those individuals and i say
that because i do
optimistically maybe naively believe
that there's a big critical mass of
people
that want to make a change and i'd
rather we focus our collective energies
on galvanizing that collective consensus
and effort
rather than focusing on people that will
you know who want to think in this way
and
that for me is a choice you know it's
not like you know what they found what
they found their beliefs on
in the first instance is based on a
supremacy
that positions black people
people of color as deficit so if that is
something they want to engage with
then i personally wouldn't waste my
money
because i do believe as i said
potentially maybe naively that there's a
greater mass of people that want to
embody change and to see it reflected
in all of its intersectional forms in
this specific case
race
um so the next question that's okay so
the next question is on
fame lecturers um lecturers may be
victimized and further discriminated and
they speak out again so i just noticed
in one of the comments that
um a colleague of ours just spoke about
you know in many cases
actually fame colleagues who engage in
this endeavor are seen as troublemakers
and i think that's it's it's a difficult
thing i think that
that that placement of the head above
the parapet becomes really really
dangerous for being colleagues who
already reside in a very toxic
environment and we kind of think of
the ball of higher education the soil
itself is toxic because
it doesn't allow professional staff
to grow in the way that they should i
think this is where allyship becomes a
really really
important term and i think thinking
about how why
um allies can engage in this space is
important because
all too often as i mentioned before the
labor of this work
particularly it's laid at the feet of
women of color and
that further discrimination what does it
look like in real terms it looks like a
lack of promotion
by complete alienation from department
teams it looks like a lack of agents
it looks like a lack of it and ends up
becoming salary differential
so i do think it's really important that
you know what white allyship looks like
going forward must look to disrupt these
spaces it can't be left to just blame
individuals
to disrupt these spaces when in many
cases they don't have the power or the
privilege to advance that agenda
not because they themselves don't have a
power and a personal privilege
but because those spaces don't
acknowledge or accept
that power and that privilege and we
know that the centrality of whiteness
is what occupies that particular
structure of racism as we see it so i do
think that it's important that we think
about
how white relationship can be
reconceptualized to really
take the labor of this work off fame
individual thought and sorry in relation
to the last part in terms of
what do you do to protect yourself from
this i i don't i don't think there is
anything that can protect one from this
to be honest
i think what can be um
what can be kind of configured is really
thinking about how that labor
or that burden can be lifted and i think
because the idea of protecting
oneself i think it's a very difficult
thing just because of how
insidious racism is
and the last question senior leaders
and in terms of senior leaders i think
the biggest thing that we've kind of all
collectively mentioned is this idea of
money
i think that it's really really
important to think about how we engage
with
human resource and fiscal resource and
i think and i don't want to label this
at all senior leaders but i think
there's a lot of cd leaders who've been
absent you know they've been absent from
this discussion for many many years and
where we've seen
really pertinent advancements in gender
equality
um in fe and in higher education we
don't actually see that in
um we haven't seen that with regards to
race
and i think one of the things that's
kind of really central to these
arguments
is that you know often race work or race
interventions such as the wreck
are not funded and we kind of need to
think about okay
you know if it isn't funded in the same
way that athena swan was
then how do we actually think about
funding these things
um internally and i think the internal
funding of this and resourcing of this
is really really important and more
important than that it needs to be
institutional wide
so too often you get a localized pocket
for fantastic practice within
institution
but what we need is a really collected
consensus around how we engage with this
and universities need to commit
senior leaders need to commit to this
financially because
if they don't the consequence is really
that we're going to continue to have
a racist academy and
invariably you know the individuals who
benefit from this
who who are most significantly
disadvantaged from this next poor
academy
are fame um staff and i think we do need
to think about
how we engage in better outcomes for
them
better progression you know ideally i
think to kind of
change the discourse in the next kind of
thing we also need to see a
diversification of fame leaders
and i think that would also change some
of the conversations that we have around
race and racism and how we occupy
certain spaces
but i do think that this is really
really important and
for me i think that again there is a
collective consensus among senior
leaders
that now is the time to act and now is
the time to
you know invest um significantly
and over a strategic period of time in
these endeavors in both the fe
and higher education sector
thank you um okay so so now uh
a couple of minutes on um summing up
um juliana
well um what i would like to see is
institutions telling
us telling and showing us what they're
doing to decolonize
their institutions not just us telling
them what they should be doing but what
what are they doing what are they doing
about their curriculum what are they
doing about stuffing
what are they doing about promotion of
black staff
you know and how are they doing it you
know um
and how much resources are they putting
into this program just the following
from what
um jason has said um
how much link do they have the black
communities
uh in this country and and other than
just overseas and recruiting
overseas students and making money out
of them you know what are their goals
for the black
communities um you know um about their
resources
how are they bringing it up today to
meet the needs of the black community
and all students for that matter
so we really need to look at you know
what programs that they're carrying
forward
and and how they are approaching these
things
thank you jason coming up
yeah just to thumb up um i think one of
the most important things is that
um in terms of thinking about
you know what we need to do moving
forward again um just to reiterate i
think a collective consensus is really
important i think
there has to be an acknowledgement that
over a prolonged period of time
and if we just look at this from a
historical perspective the work of
decolonization has really
laid at the feet unfairly laid at the
feet of
um women of color and i do think that
that is something
i know i keep going on about it i've got
to run about in several platforms but i
do think it's a really important thing
because i think how we think about
the labor of that work is very very
important going forward
because i think that yes fame
individuals collectively
are exhausted from this but actually we
need to think about how we
all engage in this work to remove that
work from being women because
you know if we look at edi departments
if we look at um
most of the engagement that happens in
this across institutions across the uk
it is often women that engage in this
endeavor women of color and i do think
we all need to think about
the burden of those women of color over
such a long period and how we all look
to engage in that collectively to
alleviate that burden
and make a collective endeavor rather
than an individually focused one
uh great thank you um i've i've learned
so much from
um both of you today um it's been really
great what what i would sort of
emphasize um from what i was saying um
two things one is to um to really take
the
um to keep students central
uh i think i think that's very important
um
because if they're not they're not part
of this
it it doesn't um it's not gonna happen
um so so so that's that's really really
important um and and also don't just
leave it to
it's it's not just about certain
subjects
it's it's about the institutions as a
whole that's the whole point of
um of what we've been talking about
today so
so i think that that's really important
too um
okay so um so thank you everyone
for um uh for clicking on to this
and i was gonna say tuning in but it's
not tuning in
um is it now um uh we've
hopefully it's been helpful to you uh we
in the black members standing committee
have been helping to produce a number of
different types of resources um
on this work on on decolonizing on on
what it could mean and um
most most of that is on the on the
website on the ucu
website um and also it there's a
there's a you can see on the screen
there's a
there's a link um to it now um
so so basically um thank you
thank you um all for for clicking on
thank you
to the other contributors my colleagues
in the black members standing committee
um thank you thank you rebecca and um
and also
thank you to to chris
nicholas who made this possible um
we wouldn't have been doing this if it
wasn't for him um
also please please keep on um
if you are interested in this please
keep on sending in
um your questions um let us know if you
want more sessions
like this and yeah stay safe
be well thank you everyone have a good
day
uh maybe jason now will sing to us
because we have finished early but
i'm not sure
hello i'm going to want again
[Laughter]
oh
thank you bye